Yeah, the title of this section
这一节的标题
is "Thanks, Tim."
是“谢谢，蒂姆”
Tim being Englishman Tim Berners-Lee.
蒂姆即英国人蒂姆·伯纳斯-李
If you haven't heard of him, we hadn't either.
如果你没听说过他，我们也没有
The Web has been the most transformative invention of our time.
万维网是我们这个时代最具革命性的发明
I use the Web to stay connected with my family.
我上网来和家人保持联系
I usually use the Web to, like,
我一般上网来
search for information, like Google.
搜索信息，比如谷歌
I use it more, like, business,
我更多地用它做商务往来
'cause I'm, like, a Web developer.
因为我是网页开发者
I use the Web for everything.
我做什么都上网
I spend, like, half my day on it.
一天里我要花半天在这上面
In modern times,
当今
I don't think there's a single piece of technology
我认为没有任何技术
that has done more to advance free expression and access to knowledge and democracy than the Web.
比万维网在推进言论自由、知识获取和民主上做得更多
I'm a scientist, so I use the Internet to read scientific papers
我是科学家，所以我用互联网读科学论文
and keep up with the news in my field.
跟上我研究领域里的新闻
Our entire business is actually run through the Web.
实际上我们所有的业务都在万维网上
So, without the Internet, we wouldn't be able to function.
所以没有互联网的话，我们会无法正常运转
It's the most important thing right now.
这是现在最重要的东西了
If the Web goes down now, the world stops.
如果万维网现在下线，世界就停止了
Literally.
真的
Who invented the World Wide Web?
谁发明了万维网？
No idea. No idea...
不知道。不知道……
Um... Who invented
呃……谁发明了……
Um...
呃……
the World Wide Web.
……万维网
It was someone in the CIA.
是 CIA 的某人吗
Oh, shoot. I should know this.
噢，我去，我应该知道的
I'm a computer science student.
我是计算机科学的学生
Um...
呃……
Steve?
史蒂夫？
Is his name Steve?
他名字叫史蒂夫吗？
No.
不
Bill Gates?
比尔·盖茨？
* 曾任美国副总统（1993 - 2001），任内提出了美国信息高速公路法案，
推动了互联网的快速发展
Al Gore*?
阿尔·戈尔*？
Siri?
I can Google it for you.
我能谷歌一下
Internet. Web.
互联网  网络
I can use the Web.
我可以上网
There are thousands of people
数以千计的人
who are probably more famous than Tim Berners-Lee.
他们也许都比蒂姆·伯纳斯-李有名得多
杰夫·贾菲
万维网联盟执行董事长
And yet, not one of them has had the impact of Tim Berners-Lee.
然而他们中没有一个人比蒂姆·伯纳斯-李的影响力大
It says Tim Bren Lee.
这里说是蒂姆·布伦-李
Is it Tim Berners-Lee?
是蒂姆·伯纳斯-李吗？
Tim...
蒂姆……
No, I haven't.
没听说过
For what he's created, it's kind of a surprise that we don't know who he is.
我们竟然不知道这是他创造出来的，这让我有点吃惊
乔纳森·斯特兰
法律与计算机科学教授
The fact that they might not have heard of Tim
人们没听说过蒂姆
is thanks to Tim.
是托蒂姆的福
蒂姆·伯纳斯-李
万维网发明者
Oh, I'm very happy that I'm not a household name.
噢，我很高兴我并不是家喻户晓
I think that must be... must be very horrible.
我觉得那会是……会是非常恐怖的
I am the son of mathematicians.
我是数学家的儿子
My mother and father were part of a team
我父母在一起工作
that programmed the world's first commercial
编写世界上第一台商业的
stored program computer — the Manchester University Mark 1.
存储程序计算机——曼彻斯特大学马克一号
I was looking for a job.
我那时在找工作
I saw an advertisement saying,
我看见一则广告说
玛丽·李·伯纳斯-李
数学家、程序员
"mathematicians required to work on a digital computer in Manchester."
“需要数学家来在曼彻斯特的数字计算机上工作”
And I went to the reference library
然后我去文献资料库
and found out what a digital computer was.
查了一下数字计算机是什么
And it was very exciting
那实在是令人感到兴奋
because people didn't know anything about computing,
因为那时候人们对计算机技术一无所知
didn't know what they would be used for.
不知道计算机能做什么
Well, the thing about a computer
关于电脑
that I'd learned from my parents is that
我从父母那里了解到的是
it can do whatever you can imagine.
它能做任何你能想象到的事情
Once you've got a computer
只要有台电脑
what it does is up to your imagination.
它做什么完全取决于你的想象
So that is the point.
这是重点
But there was this magic threshold when you had a computer.
但有了电脑才能打开新世界的大门
We were very lucky. We had four children.
我们非常幸运  我们有四个孩子
Tim was the first.
蒂姆是老大
He was always very curious.
他对这个世界充满好奇
When he was about five months,
他五个月大的时候
a professional photographer came to the house.
一名摄影师来我们家
And the photographer had a tripod
摄影师有个三角架
and lights and wires.
有几盏灯、有几根线
And Tim was amazed.
蒂姆感到非常惊奇
He was very curious.
他真的很好奇
Tried to work out how things went.
试图弄清楚每件事的来龙去脉
I suppose as a kid I was a bit geeky
我感觉我小的时候有点古怪
but also liked building things.
但也很喜欢创造些什么
He was very useful as the engineer around the house.
他就像家里的工程师一样
I had various communications devices.
我有些通讯设备
Some of which worked more than others.
其中有些设备比另外的更有用
When he was in residence, we had a very good intercom between the top floor and the kitchen.
他住家里的时候，从顶楼到厨房的通讯状况非常棒
We did feel that we should encourage him
我们确实认为应该鼓励他
in what he wanted to do.
去做他想做的事情
We tended to give the children as much freedom as we could
我们倾向于尽可能地给予孩子自由
to let them follow their bent.
去做他们感兴趣的事
The motto was "watchful negligence."
有句话是“小心地放手”
You know, keep them safe,
就是说，确保他们的安全
but let them discover the world.
同时又让他们探索这个世界
One day, I found my father reading books on the brain,
有一天，我发现我父亲正在读一本关于大脑的书
looking for clues about how to make a computer intuitive,
寻找如何让计算机拥有直觉
able to complete connections as the brain does.
能够像大脑一样发展出关系的线索
Computers were good at logical organizing and processing, and processing,
计算机在逻辑组织和处理上做得很好
but not at random associations.
但随机的关联不行
We discussed the point,
我们讨论了这一点
then I went on to my homework.
然后我继续做作业去了
But the idea stayed with me
但这个想法伴随着我
that computers could be much more powerful
计算机是可以变得更加强大的
if they could be programmed to link
如果计算机能被编程来关联
otherwise unconnected information.
本没有被关联的信息
In an extreme view,
极端点说
the world can be seen as only connections.
世界可以被看作是完全由连结组成的
We think of a dictionary as the repository of meaning,
我们把词典想象成是一个意义的仓库
but it defines words only in terms of other words.
它只是在用别的词来定义一个词
There's really little else to meaning.
真的没什么别的含义了
There are billions of neurons in our brains,
我们的大脑有数以亿计的神经元
but the brain has no knowledge until connections are made between the neurons.
直到神经元之间建立起连接之前，大脑都不拥有知识
What matters is the connections.
重要的是连接
There were many different people
以前有很多人
蒂莉·布莱思
伦敦科学博物馆馆长
who thought about how you might categorize and link
想过可以怎样分类、关联
and share information,
并且分享信息
right back to the 19th century.
就在十九世纪的时候
A guy called Paul Otlet actually developed
保罗·欧特雷提出了
this idea of a world brain.
世界大脑的概念
A place where all the information could be held.
一个能存下所有信息的地方
And you could send in an inquiry,
你可以向其发起查询
and you would get a result
然后就能得到结果
thanks to women who would go through the card catalog
因为里面有负责遍历卡片目录的职员
and find out the answer for you.
帮你找到答案
When you move to the Information Age,
进入信息时代
lots of different people were working to develop
许多人便开始开发
digital electronic computers.
数字电子计算机
We have a pointing device called a mouse,
这里有一个指点设备叫鼠标
standard keyboard,
标准键盘
and then I'm going to jump to a link.
然后我会跳转到一个链接上
Ted Nelson came up with the original idea of hypertext —
泰德·尼尔森提出了超文本的原始观点
linking information,
关联信息
creating text that would link from one section to another.
写出能从一个地方链接到另一个地方的文本
But it moves through to the development of the Internet in the 1960s
这一概念贯穿了互联网在二十世纪六十年代的发展
and then the World Wide Web in 1990s.
以及九十年代的万维网
The Web is the user-friendly version of the Internet.
万维网是用户友好的互联网
The Internet
互联网
the basic underlying network
最基础的网络
was too complicated for people.
对大众来说太复杂了
Tim pared away
蒂姆消除了
丹尼尔·魏茨纳
麻省理工学院信息政策项目主任
a lot of the complexity
大量的复杂环节
and made the Internet accessible to everyone.
使所有人都得以访问互联网
The NeXT computer
NeXT 计算机
in which Tim Berners-Lee originally designed the World Wide Web
蒂姆·伯纳斯-李在上面设计了万维网
it looks very boring, it's just a black box.
这玩意看起来很无趣，不过是个黑盒子
It doesn't say very much about how important and how historic it is,
看不出它有多么重要、多么具有历史意义
apart from that one little label on the front
除了那张贴在机箱前面的小标签
that says, "This machine is a server.
写着  这台机器是服务器
Do not power it down."
不要关机
And so, if somebody had turned off the computer,
所以，如果那时有人关掉了这台电脑
they would have turned off the World Wide Web,
他就会关掉万维网
which is just inconceivable to us today.
对今天的我们而言简直不可思议
CERN 总部
瑞士日内瓦
CERN is an international physics lab in Switzerland,
CERN 是在瑞士的国际物理实验室
built in '54.
设立于 1954 年
12 countries funded it, and then they said,
十二个国家对它投资，然后他们说
佩琪·里默
物理学家
"Anybody in the world who wants to do an experiment here,
世界上想在这里做实验的的任何人
"we provide all the facilities, you can do it,
我们提供所有的设施，你可以来做
"so long as you can convince us that you can do it.
只要你能说服我们你能做到
"You bring your own equipment, you bring your own brains,
带上你的设备、你的头脑
and we'll supply everything else you need."
我们会提供所有你需要的其他东西
I came in as a contract programmer
我以合同工程序员的身份加入
and then became a staff member.
然后我又成为了职工
He was entirely charming.
他真的太帅了
In our section meetings,
在小组会议上
we all had to say what we were doing each week sometimes,
有时每人都要说一下这周的工作小结
and Tim used to give his little presentations.
然后蒂姆会开始他的表演
Now, I used to watch this and think,
现在再看当时的录像，就感觉
"What is actually going on here?"
“这都是啥玩意啊？”
What are all the things which he's written which have not been d... which have not got... which are not described by documents, which he has also written, which are used by things which are recursively transit[ive] closure of... used by things... which are used by anything which I'm relying on?
所有他写的没有被他写的被某些别的递归地形成传递闭包的
被另一些我依赖的东西使用的东西使用的文档描述的东西是什么？
We could never understand what he was talking about.
我们从来不知道他在说什么
He'd start a sentence... he'd start his thought,
在说一个句子的时候……他会开始思考
start a sentence, and then by the time he got...
开始说话，然后等说到……
the first third, say, his thoughts had gone past that now.
比如三分之一的时候，他的思想已经走得很远了
So he'd drop the next bit,
所以他会省略接下来的句子
not tell you what was in the middle,
不告诉你中间的内容
and finish the sentence.
然后结束句子
Some of his colleagues, some of our friends
他的同事，有些也是我们的朋友
used to get bits of paper and hold them up,
会举起几张纸来打信号
and it would just say, "Tim, slow down."
表示“蒂姆，慢一点”
Oh, these are... these are my people.
噢，他们是……他们是自己人
These are all the people who know to do this when I speak too fast.
他们知道要在我说得太快的时候这么做
Okay. I will try.
好吧，我尽力
His brain is so peculiarly wired up.
他异常地擅长融会贯通
It's fabulously wired up, but it's not very common
不只是普通意义上的擅长，很难碰到
to find people who think kind of...
有人的思考模式会如此地……
I don't know... all at once.
怎么说呢……一步到位
So there I was at CERN
那时我在 CERN
wonderfully creative, wonderfully diverse place.
一个非常有创意、非常多样的地方
People have come from all over the world.
人们来自世界的各个角落
They've come from different universities,
来自不同的大学
and there's no big rules written on the wall at CERN
CERN 也没有什么清规戒律
that say you can only use one particular computer.
规定你只能用哪台电脑
Incompatibility between computers
计算机间的不兼容
had always been a huge pain in everyone's side
对任何人来说都无比痛苦
at CERN and everywhere else they were used.
无论是在 CERN，还是在别的地方
The computers simply could not communicate with each other.
计算机就是没法互相通信
You imagine if you've got power plugs.
你想像一下，你有几个电源插头
You're sitting in an office with
你坐在办公室里
Every power plug is different.
每个插头都是不一样的
Okay, what's wrong with this picture?
好吧，这有什么问题呢
So the first thing you do is you make a cable to connect
你首先要做根线
power plug A to power plug C.
来连接插头 A 和插头 C
And then you realize that you need to connect, oh,
然后你发现还要连接
one of the Fs to a G.
F 之中的一个和 G
*&^%$#@
So, after a while, if you were doing this with power plugs,
所以，过不了多久，如果你还是在搞电源插头
you'd say, "Do you know what? I've had enough of this.
你就会说  搞什么？我不干了
"I am going to make my own standard power plug,
我要自己造电源插头的转接头
"which is gonna be very flexible,
这个插头非常灵活
"it's gonna do everything I want,
能做我想做的一切
and I'm just gonna convert all of them to that."
我就能把这些插头全转换成那一种
"Suppose all the information stored on computers everywhere
我设想，如果计算机上存储的所有信息
were linked," I thought.
都有关联
Suppose I could program my computer
如果我能给我的计算机编程
to create a space in which anything could be linked to anything.
来创造一个空间，里面的一切都可以相互关联
All the bits of information in every computer in CERN
CERN 里所有计算机的所有信息
and on the planet would be available to me
甚至整个地球上的，我都能看到
and anyone else.
并且其他人也能看到
There would be this single global information space.
这样就有了一整个的全球信息空间
I would have to create a system with common rules
我就要创建一个有秩序的系统
that would be acceptable to everyone.
任何人都认同并接受
That meant as close as possible to no rules at all.
这意味着几乎没什么规矩
The system had to have one other fundamental property.
这个系统还必须要有另一个基本属性
It had to be completely decentralized.
它一定是完全去中心化的
That would be the only way a new person from somewhere
这是唯一能让萌新
could start to use it without asking for access
马上能开始使用这个系统的方法
from anyone else.
而无须获取另一个人的许可
Anybody could build a server and put anything on it.
任何人都能设立服务器，放任何东西上去
He set out to build a platform
他去构建了一个平台
that would enable people to share and link information.
让人们分享并关联信息
It was specifically designed so that, potentially,
万维网是精心设计过的，因此潜在地
every single piece of information in the world
世界上的每一条信息
could be represented on the Web.
在万维网上都能予以呈现
Now, that's a big concept.
这是个很宏大的概念
A lot of people heard that
很多人听说了之后
and thought it was kind of crazy.
觉得这有点疯狂
I don't think anybody thought it was crazy.
我不认为有人觉得它疯狂
You have to understand something before you can say it's crazy,
你至少要懂一点，才能说什么东西很疯狂
and we never got that far.
而我们并不懂
I think people thought it was interesting.
我认为大家觉得这很有趣
"Vague but exciting." Dot, dot, dot.
好像很刺激的样子  点点点
Nobody really joined me and said, "Ooh.
没人加入，没人说  喔喔喔
Let's all code that up!"
我们来编程吧
Um, you know, before the Web, nobody could imagine it.
呃，你要知道，在万维网诞生之前，没人想象得到
I don't think I can describe how Tim's mind works.
我觉得我没法解释蒂姆的大脑是怎么转的
Tim is the most out-of-the-box thinker that I've come across,
蒂姆是我见过的最能跳出思维定式的人
and I've come across quite a lot of out-of-the-box thinkers.
我可是见过很多能跳出思维定式的人的
So what should I call it?
那么我该怎么叫它？
I thought about The Information Mine* — TIM.
我想过 The Information Mine*——TIM
* “信息宝库”
That would not be very good,
这不是太好
and Mine of Information would have been "MOI*,"
Mine of Information 又会变成 MOI*
* Moi 为法语“我”
also not very — I'm so sorry —
也不是很——抱歉——
Bit egotistical.
有点自大
Call it Mesh.
叫 Mesh 吧
Mesh just sounded too meshy.
Mesh 听起来很 Meshy（纠缠）
* “我从 Mesh 里找到了”
"I got it out of the mesh."
“我摆脱了 Mesh（混乱）”*
"Here's option A, here's option B.
“有选项 A，有选项 B”
What... what do you think, Tim?"
“你怎么想，蒂姆？”
I mean, he'll always favor option C.
我的意思是，他总是会倾向于选项 C
So I called it the World Wide Web
所以我称它做万维网
because that's what it was.
因为它就是那样的
It was supposed to be global, and it was supposed to be a web.
它应该是全球的，并且应该是张网
But we said, "Tim, this is crazy,
但是我们说  蒂姆，这很疯狂
"because your acronym, the shortened form,
因为你这缩写，简写形式
"is three times more syllables than the original.
有三倍于全称的音节
So isn't this a bit, you know — and you can't pronounce it."
这是不是有点，怎么说呢——你还没法读出来
We can, at a distance, work together
我们可以隔着一段距离，一起工作
and develop documents together without anything impeding us.
一起撰写文档，而完全不受阻碍
My first convert, Robert Cailliau,
我的第一个迷弟，罗伯特·卡里奥
then became my partner,
之后成为我的搭档
trying to persuade people to use the Web as a resource.
试图说服人们把万维网看作是资源来使用
In July and August 1991,
在 1991 年的 7 月到 8 月里
there were from 10 to 100 hits a day.
每天都有 10 到 100 次的点击
This was slow progress, but encouraging.
进程缓慢，但很振奋人心
Robert Cailliau and I forged ahead
罗伯特·卡里奥和我继续推进
and showed the Web as much as possible.
尽可能地展示万维网
There was no one point when it was clearly gonna take off.
万维网不是一蹴而就的
We never had time to sit back and say,
我们从来没有机会坐下说
"You know what?
你知道吗
I bet this thing is going to take over the planet."
我赌这玩意会占领整个地球
It just didn't happen.
就没发生过
In 1993, I once again graphed the number of people
1993 年，我又画了一张图表
who are accessing the CERN server.
描绘访问 CERN 服务器的人的数量
It was now taking 10,000 hits a day.
那时每天有一万次点击了
The rate was incredible
这个速度十分惊人
still doubling every three or four months,
每三到四个月就翻倍
growing by a factor of ten every year.
每年就增长十倍
Keeping this young system
让这个年轻的系统
on track...
走上正轨
just needed so many different things.
需要很多不同的东西（去维护）
What should CERN do about it?
CERN 要做什么呢
Should we start a company?
我们应该开家公司吗
He got CERN to agree
蒂姆让 CERN 同意
that Tim could take all of the intellectual property
他可以拿走他的所有围绕着
that he had built up around the Web
万维网的知识产权
and make it available freely to the world.
让万维网对全世界自由可用
It meant that people could develop Websites freely,
这意味着人们可以自由地开发网站
without thinking about who they had to pay.
而不需要考虑要先给谁付钱
And probably more importantly, it meant that a whole crop
也许更重要的是，这还意味着一大堆的
of software companies could develop around the Web.
软件公司能够围绕万维网做开发
These were little start-ups.
这些都是小创业公司
They didn't have money
他们没有钱
to pay big companies licensing fees.
去给大公司付授权费
But they were on the leading edge
但他们在塑造万维网这件事情上
of really shaping what the Web looked like.
是占据领先地位的
James Gleick famously called the Web
詹姆斯·格雷克把万维网称作
"the patent that never was."
“前所未有的专利”
Had Tim wanted to figure out how to commercialize it,
如果蒂姆想过怎么把它商业化
there were many off-ramps
有过很多次机会
by which he could have tried to do that,
他本来都可以做到的
and he resolutely never did.
但他坚决不这么做
It was an incredibly altruistic decision to make,
他做了非常无私的决定
but I also think it was a very hard-nosed decision to make
不过我还觉得这是个非常强硬的决定
because he wanted the Web to succeed.
因为他希望万维网成功
If Tim hadn't given away the World Wide Web protocols,
如果蒂姆没有把万维网协议贡献出来
you wouldn't seen nearly the same uptake.
你大概就看不到同样的进程了
温顿·瑟夫
互联网共同创始人
Free is pretty hard to argue about.
自由是很难争论的一件事
Bob Kahn and I did the same thing.
鲍勃·卡恩和我做了同样的事情
And Tim has said to me that he followed that path,
蒂姆也跟我说过他是步我的后尘
understanding how powerful it had been for the Internet
理解了互联网的强大之处
and wanted the same effect for the World Wide Web.
并且希望万维网对这个世界有一样的影响
We are all trying to organize our thoughts.
我们总是尝试组织我们的思想
We are all trying to figure out how this all fits together,
我们都在探寻把这一切放到一起的方法
whether we're trying to find a way to build bridges
不论是去找建桥的方法
or we're trying to find a way to run government.
还是去找运作政府的方法
The Web is a great way of doing it
万维网是做到这些的绝佳之道
because you can instantly get at other people's attempts.
因为一瞬间你就能看到前人的尝试
You can put in your little two cents worth of link.
你甚至可以放你自己的链接上去
I remember very, very clearly
我记得非常、非常清楚
when I first encountered the World Wide Web.
我第一次见到万维网的时候
Marc Andreessen developed something called Mosaic,
马克·安德森开发了“马赛克”
which was one of the first World Wide Web browsers.
是第一批万维网浏览器之中的一个
And this stunned everyone,
震惊了所有人
because suddenly the Internet was this beautiful,
因为一下子互联网变得如此漂亮
colorful, interactive thing.
如此多彩，还能互动
It had never been anything like that before.
前无古人，后无来者
One new server impressed me.
一台新服务器让我记忆深刻
It was a server of information
那是一台记录着
about Rome during the Renaissance.
文艺复兴时期的罗马的服务器
I wandered into the music room. I clicked.
我走进了“音乐厅”，我点击鼠标
I was glad I had a 21-inch Colorstream.
我很高兴我那时有台 21 英寸的显示器
Suddenly, it was filled
一瞬间，显示器充满了
with this beautiful and illuminated score,
漂亮至极、发光发亮的乐谱
which I could gaze at probably more easily and in more detail
我能盯着它看，还能更容易地看到更多细节
than I could have done had I gone to the original exhibit.
比我去原始展览要好得多
It was a great example of how a combination of effort
这是各种工作组合起来的绝佳例子
from around the world could lead to fantastic things.
从世界的各地来，为世界带来美妙
You can now glimpse the future
现在就可以瞥上一眼未来的样子
with nothing more than a modem, a phone line,
只需要调制解调器、电话线
and a few dollars a month.
还有每月几刀的费用
At this point, we're starting to see
在这个时候，我们已经开始看到
the beginnings of a total explosion.
一场爆炸式改变的开始
The global village has arrived.
全球村就在眼前
You need a computer and a phone,
一台电脑一座电话
and suddenly you're part of a new mesh of people,
然后你摇身一变，成了新新人类
programs, archives, ideas.
程序、存档、想法
This thing became available called the Web.
这个叫做万维网的新东西
And all of a sudden, it was easy to get information.
让获取信息突然变得容易了
The democratic potential of the Web
万维网的民主潜能
was apparent right away.
当时就十分显眼
I was working in Washington
我在华盛顿工作
as a public-policy advocate,
做政策游说
and people started to put the legislative proposals on the Web.
人们开始上传议案到网上
And all of a sudden, the disparate power over information became equalized.
一瞬间就把信息差打破了
I could see the same information
我能看到的信息
that the most high-priced lobbyist could see,
和高价说客能看到的一样
and that was incredibly exciting.
这非常振奋人心
It's a completely different dimension.
完全不在一个维度上
If you enable people to not just broadcast
当人们可以不局限于
from one central point out to many others...
只从一个中心向外广播
But actually to start to communicate between each other,
而开始可以真正地互相沟通
you're enabling lots of people to become broadcasters.
更多的人可以成为主播
And you bring down a lot of, you know,
这也打破了很多
traditional hierarchies
那些控制信息传播的
that control who has access to information.
传统阶级
[man speaking Spanish]
「西班牙语」
In Guatemala, there are 24 different languages.
危地马拉有 24 种语言
The open Web gave the possibility
开放的万维网让 24 群不同语言的使用者
雷娜塔·艾维拉
万维网基金会活动家
for these 24 linguistic communities
有机会制作线上节目
to start producing online radio and their own content
制作他们专属的内容
as a way to preserve their culture.
来传承他们的文化
Suddenly, there is an avalanche of content
突然间，内容像雪崩一样产生
being generated by ordinary people
制作者都是普通人
who have ideas and things that they want to share with other people.
他们有主意、有事情想别人分享
Even though they weren't getting reimbursed for it,
即使一分钱不赚
they got gratification that something they knew
他们收获的是满足感
was useful to somebody else.
自己的知识对他人有用
For the nerds among us,
对我们这群怪咖来说
the Internet and the Web are a standing invitation
互联网和万维网是无法忽视的邀请
to build that Website
建立网站
and to build with whatever tools
在过程中利用任何工具
fit well in your hand
只要自己觉得合适
and see what bits beat a path to your door.
然后看看什么会带来流量
It is the story of Netscape,
这是网景的故事
and it is the story of our time.
也是我们的故事
They're calling him the next Bill Gates.
别人都叫他下一个比尔盖茨
Hi, YouTube. This is Chad and Steve.
嗨，YouTube 用户，我们是查德和史蒂夫
We're the co-founders of the site.
是这个网站的创始人
Google will pay $1.6 billion to gobble up YouTube.
Google 会斥资 16 亿收购 YouTube
eBay has agreed to acquire GSI Commerce
eBay 确认了收购 GSI Commerce
for $2.4 billion.
标额 24 亿美元
Valued between $130 billion,$150 billion —
估值在 1300 亿到 1500 亿之间
The biggest Internet IPO since Google.
Google 以来最大的互联网企业 IPO
Excitement on the trading floor was palpable.
交易所充满了激动的气氛
Millionaires and billionaires were minted today.
今天铸就了多个百万富翁和亿万富翁
People have asked me whether I'm upset
有人问我后不后悔
that I haven't made a lot of money from the Web.
没有用万维网赚一笔大的
In fact, I've made quite conscious decisions
实际上，我有意作出了这样的决定
about which directions to lead my life.
来实现我的人生价值
What does distress me, though,
而真正让我感到忧虑的
is how important a question it seems to be to some.
是一个问题，这个问题对某些人又有多重要
Core in my upbringing was a value system
我小时候受到的价值观教育
that put monetary gain well in its place
把金钱利益的位置摆得很正
behind things like doing what I really want to do.
放在我真正想做的事情后面
Tim did two really important things
蒂姆在万维网最开始的时候
at the very beginning of the Web.
就做了两件很关键的事情
Number one, he designed the Web.
第一，他设计了万维网
He wrote a paper that said
他写了一篇文档
here's what the World Wide Web should look like.
给出了万维网的布局
And number two, he built an institution,
第二，他设立了一个机构
the World Wide Web Consortium,
万维网联盟
that could develop and help the Web to grow.
来开发和发展万维网
It we spend a whole — a certain amount of time
我们花很长时间使用互联网
using the Internet, we have to spend a little part of —
我们也必须花一小部分时间
a little proportion of that time defending it,
来守卫互联网
worrying about it, looking out for it.
关心它，照顾它
What the Web is becoming is a platform
万维网正在变成一个平台
for collective problem solving and mass participation.
来利用集体解决问题，让人们参与进来
We need to put in place policies that extend access
我们要有政策来确保
for people with disabilities.
残疾人也可以正常使用
So the World Wide Web Consortium is a group
万维网联盟是一个协会
of companies and individuals and organizations of different types
由各种各样的公司、个人、团体组成
all trying to figure out,
共同探索
how can we make the Web more powerful,
怎么让万维网变得更强大
how can we make it, in a way, more fairer,
更公平
but keeping it one Web?
同时保持一个整体？
Tim certainly took care of his baby.
蒂姆为打理他的宝贝发明做了很多事
I mean, he really, really did.
我是说，真的
And he cares deeply
他十分在乎
that it should end up being what he wanted it to be.
万维网应该达成最开始的使命蓝图
For the last 25 years, whenever somebody's asked me
过去的 25 年里，每次有人问我
about what my biggest fear is, I think I always said
什么最让我担忧，我几乎每次都回答
that some company or government or combination
最怕某些公司、政府，或是两者一起
should end up controlling the Web.
最后会掌控万维网
The Internet has always treated every customer the same,
互联网总是平等对等每个消费者
but this morning the net neutrality principle
但今天，互联网中立原则
faces a historic change.
受到了历史性的改变
Abandoning net neutrality
废除网络中立
would threaten to end the Internet as we know it.
预示着终结我们习以为常的互联网
Americans want net neutrality!
美国人要网络中立！
85% of Republican voters...
85% 的共和党选民
(Both) ... want net neutrality!
（两人）要求网络中立！
How would I explain net neutrality?
怎么解释网络中立呢
Yeah, it's not very easy. [Laughs]
嗯……不是很容易解释（笑）
Yes, net neutrality,
对，网络中立
the only two words that promise more boredom
英语里比这两个单词还无聊的
in the English language are "featuring Sting."
可就算是“斯汀出演”了
People hear the word "net neutrality,"
人们听到“网络中立”这个词
and their eyes glaze over, but this is truly important.
就变得不感兴趣，但这真的很重要
Net neutrality is that all content travels
网络中立是指所有内容
at the same speed.
都以相同的速度传播
It's neutral.
是中立的
It should.
应该这样
Well, and it has.
实际上，它就是
It has from the beginning.
从最开始就是这样
The way that the Web works today
万维网目前的运行方式
fits the definition of net neutrality.
就是网络中立的定义
The Web is like a highway.
万维网就像公路
Anyone can circulate freely,
所有人都可以自由行驶
and it doesn't matter that your car is a Ferrari.
无论你的车是不是法拉利
It doesn't matter if you're on a bike.
就算你骑车也无所谓
There's certain regulations just in place
正好也有些监管条例
to keep things flowing in an efficient way.
来确保运作效率
Now, think about a place where, because of what you're driving,
现在，想象一下你会因为驾驶车辆的不同
you will be forced to take a different highway
被迫到另一条更窄的路上
that is more restricted, that has more checkpoints.
一条有更多检查站的路上
That doesn't make sense,
这不符合逻辑
because we have one road system.
我们只有一个交通系统
It's really important that you can go
能自由穿梭于各地
from anywhere to anywhere.
是十分重要的
The idea of making it dependent
把这和驾驶什么车挂钩
on what sort of car you're driving is just crazy.
完全就是荒诞的想法
Imagine a country of ten thousand cities
想象下有一万座城市的国家
where you can only visit five.
但你只能去其中的五座城市
That's the same when you lack net neutrality.
这就是没有网络中立的样子
There are new fears Washington may take that wide-open
有人担忧华盛顿方面会把一条宽阔的
super highway and turn it into a toll road.
超级公路变成一条收费路
The FCC is endorsing new rules
联邦通信委员会提议了新的条例
that could clear the way for a two-tier system.
给“双轨系统”开道
It would allow websites to buy faster service.
允许网站购买更快的服务
The rules would open the door for the first time
有史以来第一次
for Internet providers like Comcast and Verizon
允许 Comcast 和 Verizon 这样的互联网提供商
to charge tech companies to send content
向网络公司收费来加速
to consumers more quickly.
内容传送到消费者的过程
So now people with money
所以现在有钱的人
will have more access than people without money.
比起没钱的人，能访问到更多内容
And the whole idea behind the Internet in the first place
但互联网最初的主旨就是
was that everybody has equal access.
所有人都有平等的访问权
It's not just for rich people.
不只是富人
Everybody has access.
所有人都有
Offering fast lanes and such
提供加速链路之后
could create a world where content providers that already are big and have big wallets
不缺钱的大型内容提供商
can write checks,
可以付钱
and those that are small might be told,
但竞争者可能就会被扔到一边
"You're not worth our trouble."
“你不值得我们来费事”
If this had been in place all along,
如果最开始就是这样的话
what innovations do you think we wouldn't have now?
还会有什么创新呢
I'm not sure Twitter ever gets started.
也许不会有 Twitter
Because the cable company will say, "Twitter? This —
因为宽带公司会说：Twitter？这东西……
"How is this gonna make money for us?
这东西怎么给我们创造利润？
Forget it."
别想了
In developing countries, it becomes critical
在发展中国家，这很关键
because it can make the difference
它可以把一个
of someone living forever in ignorance and poverty
永远生活在无知和贫困中的人
to someone accessing knowledge even about their rights.
变成一个得以求知甚至争取权利的人
Russian authorities have blocked access
俄罗斯当局屏蔽了
to over 100 Websites.
百余个网站的访问
Raif Badawi published a Website promoting free speech,
雷夫·巴达沃威建立了一个宣传言论自由的网站
sometimes critical of religion.
有时对宗教持批评态度
Raif Badawi was sentenced to a total of 1,000 lashes
雷夫·巴达沃威被判刑接受 1000 下鞭打
and 10 years in prison.
和 10 年监禁
There are lots of threats,
有很多威胁
and as the Web has become more powerful
随着万维网变得更强大
and a more powerful voice of the people,
人们的声音变得更强大
more powerful instrument,
更有力地给事业作出贡献
that power has been resented by some governments.
成为被一些政府愤恨的力量
A key tool for the protesters in their fight for democracy
对为民主而斗争的抗议者来说
here in Hong Kong is the use of social media.
社交网络是个很关键的工具
We're seeing people everywhere using Twitter,
所有人都在使用 Twitter
using Facebook, Instagram.
使用 Facebook、Instagram
But there is a fear
但有人担忧
that maybe the Hong Kong government will cut reception.
香港政府可能会实施屏蔽
Nearly 40,000 Websites are inaccessible in Pakistan,
将近四万个网站无法在巴基斯坦访问
including YouTube.
包括 YouTube
Tens of thousands of protesters
千万抗议者
marching in Hungary.
在匈牙利游行
They're upset about a plan by the government to tax Internet use.
对政府征收网络税表示不满
I think things are coming to a head.
我觉得事情在一个转折点上
The stakes are bigger than they've ever been.
台面上的赌注比任何时候都要大
The rules of net neutrality.
网络中立原则
The rule that this only works because it's a neutral medium
只有保持中立才能成功的原则
isn't sufficiently well instilled.
还没有被充分认同
The World Wide Web is celebrating, this month,
这个月，万维网会庆祝
its 25th anniversary.
它的 25 周年纪念日
So I've got a question for you —
所以我要给你们一个问题——
What sort of Web do you want?
你想要什么样的网络？
We should think more about our constitutional right.
我们应该更多地思考宪法权利
It's our right in the sense of a human right
人权层面上，我们有权利
to be able to wander around the Web.
在网络上自由探索
The Web is our new world.
网络是我们的新世界
We need to be able to go wherever we want.
我们需要得以自由活动
Let's crowdsource a Bill of Rights for the Web.
让我们征集一部网络的权利法案
How about we do that?
怎么样？
How about we decide,
不如我们来决定
"These are, in a way, becoming fundamental rights,
“这些权利，某种意义上，成为了基本权利的一部分”
the right to communicate with whom I want"?
“自由和他人沟通的权利”
What would be on your list for that Magna Carta?
你会为这个大宪章提议些什么？
Tim is leading the very start of a movement
蒂姆正在领导一场运动的开始
to protect this public good that is the open Web,
来保护开放网络这一公共利益
because it's not too late yet.
因为现在还不算太迟
Tim was the one opening this gate,
蒂姆打开了这扇门
this portal in time.
新时代的大门
We had a small opening in power structures,
我们有机会改变权力分布的结构
and that was the Web.
这就是网络
Tim opened the possibility of anyone
蒂姆抛出了一个可能性
to make anything happen on the Web.
让任何人都可以在网络上做任何事
Now the clock is ticking,
现在时间紧迫
and this small gate in time and space is closing.
这扇门正在关闭
When it's closed, it's closed, and we will have an Internet
当它关上之后，就真的再也不会打开了
that is more similar to television, you know?
互联网会变得更像电视网络，你知道吗？
It is up to us,
这取决于我们
and it is difficult,
而且这很困难
but we are several millions.
但我们有百万群众
Do me a favor, will you?
你能帮我一个忙吗？
Fight for it for me, okay? Thanks.
帮我一起为其斗争，好吗？谢谢
Tim believes more than anything else
蒂姆比任何人都更加相信
that good things happen in the world when people work together.
合作能让更好的事情发生
That's how he made the Web happen.
这是我们实现网络的基石
The debate over Internet regulation
关于网络监管的辩论
has to led to a record 3.7 million user comments
引发了破纪录的 370 万条公众意见
directed at the FCC,
递交到联邦通信委员会
and less than 1% of those comments
其中反对网络中立的意见
were in opposition to net neutrality.
占比小于 1%
They took to the streets in the tens of thousands,
万人上街
and their voices have been heard.
表达了他们的声音
Hungary has dropped plans to introduce a taxon Internet use.
匈牙利取消了网络税的计划
In Mexico, the government's bid to tighten control over the use of Internet
墨西哥政府加强网络控制的尝试
is triggering anti-censorship protests.
引起了反对审查的抗议
The backlash has been so intense
抗议的高涨
that the country's ruling party is now backing down.
迫使执政党放弃了此计划
The ayes have it. The item —
多数赞成，议案——
The Federal Communications Commission today
今天，联邦通信委员会
voted 3-2 for net neutrality.
以 3 比 2 的投票结果通过了网络中立
As the outpouring from four million Americans has demonstrated,
此次四百万美国群众的参与体现了
the Internet is the ultimate vehicle for free expression.
互联网是言论自由的终极载体
This is actually the third time
这实际上是第三次
the FCC has tried to pass net neutrality rules.
联邦通信委员会试图采用网络中立法规
They've been trying this for 12 years.
他们已经尝试了 12 年
The last couple times they tried it,
前几次尝试中
they've done it in a way that wasn't legally sustainable.
他们的实现方式从法律角度无法维持
We will keep emailing, we will keep writing,
我们会继续发邮件、继续写信
we will keep fighting
继续斗争
for nothing short of real net neutrality
直到实现真正的网络中立
so that it's protected forever.
它将永远被保护
The openness of the Internet
互联网的开放性
allowed me to produce — to build the Web.
让我得以创造万维网
The openness of the Web has allowed people to build
万维网的开放性让人们得以创造
all kinds of things.
各种各样的事物
We have to make sure that
我们必须确保
that kind of innovationis preserved,
这种创新继续下去
because I'm pretty sure
因为我十分确定
there's another Tim Berners-Leeout there somewhere
下一个蒂姆·伯纳斯-李
with some really cool idea.
就在某个角落怀揣着非常厉害的想法
And there's certainly hundreds of people
当然还有许多其他人
with slightly less cool ideas.
有稍微不那么厉害的想法
And we want to have the benefit of those ideas.
我们希望得益于这些想法
You know, Vint and I have always been assailed by people
温特和我总是被那些
who just don't get a few basic differences in this world.
凡夫俗子所攻击
So we're gonna settle this right now
我们要平息这场斗争
and get this all sorted out.
把一切的问题解决
So here we go.
我们开始吧
To figure out what you're curious about and pursue it
找到你感兴趣的事情，然后追求实现它
and enjoy when it has an impact on others
享受给别人带来好处的时候
if you've done something interesting
做些有趣的事情
and worry less about whose name is being inscribed where for having done it,
不用太担心谁会因此得到名望
that seems, to me, one of the gifts
对我来说
that Tim is offering
这是蒂姆带来的一个启示
in the way in which he has handled
他在万维网的爆炸式发展中
his own role in the explosion of the Web.
贯彻的原则
The development of technology is as much about the users
技术的发展无论是对用户
and about the way that users shape and use technology
对用户塑造和使用技术的方法
as about those lone inventors.
还是对那些孤独的发明家来说都一样快
Going forward, it will be really important
在将来，有个很重要的事情就是
for us to continue to see this
我们要把网络
as a living, breathing, growing thing.
当作一个活生生的、不断成长的事物
We are all responsible for this technology,
我们都有对这个技术的责任
and we can all help shape it.
我们也可以帮忙塑造它
I used to think the problems of the world,
我曾经想，这个世界的问题
particularly now we're so global,
特别是全球化之后
are more than the human mind can manage.
是远超一个人所能胜任的
And I used to think that perhaps we would breed
我也想过，也许我们可以创造一个
a more intelligent race that could solve them.
更智能的物种来解决这些问题
But perhaps the solution
但也许真正的解决方案
is the solution of swarms.
是借助群体的力量
Look how clever ants are,
看看蚂蚁有多聪明
and they haven't got much of a brain.
而它们甚至没个像样的大脑
And so we really have to be as clever as a swarm.
我们要像这样的群体一样聪明
And the Web will do that.
万维网可以做到
So we've got to learn to use
我们必须学会
collective intelligence peacefully,
如何和平地使用群体智能
and a lot of problems will get solved that way.
然后这样解决大批的问题
The spirit of the Web was very much one
万维网的精神基本上是
of international collaboration, working together,
国际合作、共同努力
people coding up things in the middle of the night —
人们一起半夜三更地写代码
in the same spirit as the spirit of the Olympics.
就像奥林匹克精神一样
The Olympics were amazing like that.
奥林匹克在这方面相当杰出
You know, there were 15,000 volunteers.
想想看，一万五千个志愿者
A huge number of them all dancing different dances
聚在一起，跳着不同的舞蹈
in completely different costumes all doing their thing.
穿着完全不同的服饰做着各自的事情
They had me sitting there
当时我要坐在台上
and typing something on a keyboard
拿着个键盘打字
which would be sent around the auditorium.
打出全场的标语
Just before we went on stage,
上台之前
I said, "Is it okay to tweet that at the same time?"
我问了句：“我能同时发条推吗？”
It was because Tim
因为蒂姆
so casually but resolutely
如此草率却又坚决地
made this, as he put it,
做了这件事，按他的说法
in the line he was asked to tweet in the middle of the Olympics
在奥运会开幕式的紧要关头
with fully more than half of the viewers wondering, "Who is this guy?"
多数观众都在疑惑“这人谁啊”的时候
He said, "This is for everyone."
他说：“这是给所有人的”
And he meant it.
这是他的掏心话
He lived it.
他贯彻始终的原则
This is for everyone. Do with it as you please.
这是给所有人的  你爱做啥做啥
When I pressed the button,
按下按键的时候
I felt I was doing it for everybody —
我觉得我是在为所有人做这件事
for all the geeks that had collaborated internationally
为这些年全世界范围内
over the years.
协作开发的极客们
Our hope in life comes from the interconnectedness
我们生活中的希望来自于
of all the people in the world.
全世界人的互相联系
The experience of seeing the Web take off
见证了这个因千万草根的努力
by the grassroots effort of thousands
而得以腾飞的万维网
gives me a tremendous hope
我有了一个宏大的希望
that if we have the individual will,
如果人们有意志
we can collectively
我们就能协作
make of our world what we want.
塑造我们想要的世界
We are the threads
我们就像是线
holding the world together.
在一起编织了这个世界
We build it now
我们现在做好它
so that those who come later
那么后来者
will be able to create great things
就能够做出更伟大的创造
that we cannot ourselves imagine.
那些我们无法想象的创造